there we go all right well good
hello good to see you good to see you to
see you first of all thanks off thanks
right off for all the work on the
blogging I thought it's been excellent
and they're deeply appreciative of it
great I mean it was wonderful to share
it's been useful to share with several
people really enjoyed it I got some good
feedback on it and good you know so I
think it was very worthwhile yeah yeah
I'm looking forward to the next one
we're going to do together yeah yeah I
think that's our I think you've really
hit on a very interesting that the
transfected participatory thing has been
very enlightening for me and yeah you
know I'm not agreeing to that I'm just
saying yeah I can I can I can I can pick
up on the enthusiasm and some of this
stuff we communicating c'mere I would
definitely like to hear your is
participatory knowing and transfect 'iv
I'd like to hear a little bit more about
that background yeah yeah that's that's
good because I'm doing a lot of work on
that right now because I think there's
deep connections between do you I think
you need to really understand
perspectival and participatory knowing
to really get what I'm talking about
when I'm talking about dial via logos
and dialectic as a as a psycho
technology for for 40 idea logos I think
but I think that's very important also I
mean this topic is current right now
rebel wisdom just released a video Ali
and David were talking about lost kinds
of knowing and they were talking about
my work and they're also talking about
you know Gilchrist's work I just had an
amazing conversation with Ian
recorded it we both hope that he and I
can talk again it was just such a fun
conversation so I bet yeah I can really
get into his space as well so I'd love
done well yeah and I think some of the
stuff you're doing about the deep we
conceptualization of psychology as
discipline I think is relevant to his
work into mine but let's let's start
with this let's start with the with the
transgender participatory and
and I normally start from the
propositional because that's where
people are familiar and worked down to
the integral but I want to start to try
the other way and I want to brick with
you let's do some jazz and see let's see
if it works better that way because amen
brother
yeah well yeah because you know you
you've got the appropriate expertise and
depth of understanding to be good on a
good interlocutor and partner so did the
know one way I try to sometimes get
started with the participatory knowing
is I pick up on bacon Stein's
idea that even though Mayans could talk
we wouldn't understand them so even if
they could you know use propositions
with the correct syntax and everything
we wouldn't get them and the idea behind
that is because they don't have our form
of life the form of life is not a state
of consciousness that's why it's deeper
than perspective amore and what is what
does that mean well it means it means it
for I think for us as human beings and
this is what something beyond lines it
means these these these things at least
there is we we are deeply historical and
not just culturally historical we have a
evolutionary history and what does that
mean that means that evolution has done
this process of what's called you know
nice construction yeah we're organism
shaped their environment and then the
environment shapes the organisms so what
you have is you have mutual shaping
right you have got some virtual shaping
and the idea is that mutual shaping that
niche construction that generates
affordances it patterns of real
connection with in which relevance
realization intelligence can occur
because if you don't have that mutual
shaping by biology you're just lost in
combinatorial explosion right completely
that's a that frames it and then flows
it yes exactly exactly and then of
course on top of the biological shaping
mutual shaping in each construction that
we share with lines of course we have
cultural type here shapes us right so
the culture if you have go ahead right
can clean because my basic psychology
language which say on top of our basic
animal psychology yeah okay we have the
chiral
it's consciousness and art so in other
words you use the word biology there you
know my language is actually that's mind
okay at the level of the animal mind at
the level the animal is corresponds to
basic psychology refuse the perspectival
proper procedural and participatory
intuitive interactive behavioral
investment flow okay and then on top of
that we are cultural persons that
justify our actions in a secondary
reflective stance and that gives rise to
problem distich propositional systems
and actors I think this is gonna be
parallel I think so let me say some more
and then no no I think I want you to be
that you so what I was going to say is
you know cultural is a mutual shaping to
we shape the environment to fit us and
we shape ourselves to fit the
environment that's that's why you
expense culture shock when you go
somewhere else all right so you you you
don't know your biological fitness as a
set of beliefs it's not even a state of
consciousness right it's you participate
in it hence the term participatory
knowing you participate in these
construction you participate in cultural
right cultural coordination that that
will heal to admit that you're talking
about and then above and beyond that you
have cognitive mutual shaping and so
what I'm having right is I'm constantly
you can even see this and you know our
levels of sort of probability and
conditioning because the organism is not
just the idea that that's largely
associational I think is a fundamental
miss thinking of the data right right
you agree with me on that so morning we
don't need to get into discovery so no
yeah I mean evolution creates the frame
of adaptation and then there's
adjustments through Association and
operon well yeah but I even say that
even at the level of the conditioning
what you're actually seeing and this is
with no coming out and some of the more
sophisticated modeling right is you're
not you're not seeing Association your
people have moved no no what you're
seeing is prediction right and right and
then and then and there's more people
are now pointing out well it's not just
prediction
what you're seeing is prediction that's
it fused with preparation the organism
is just sort of predicting the
environment it's also preparing so right
and what does that mean the organism has
some implicit model of itself and it's
activating the appropriate skills given
that self model and given the prediction
of the environment and all of that's
happening now what does that what does
that mean you're simultaneously right
your creatures are aspectual izing the
environment they're shaping it
cognitively but they're also shaping
themselves as a here's the sequence of
operations underneath so that's your
head positive you can optimal grip down
to get up to looker right so once you're
getting up to that level right that's
where the participatory knowing now acts
as a constraining matrix within which
the prospective all-knowing unfolds as
you said within that once I have the
biological mutual shaping the cultural
mutual shaping I have what I think is
the relevance realization mutual shaping
then within that now I have right the
here nowness of my salience landscaping
and that's what the what is it like to
be sober here now right what's my
salience landscape it is it's very much
more adverbial than adjectives all right
that's a procedural and the perspectival
and the point about both of those
throughout that description is all of
that is transgender
the shape in right the shaping that
creates biological Hortons cultural
affordance called cognitive performance
cognitive affordance sensorimotor
affordance all of that is transductive
it is co-created by the environment and
the organism in a mutually coupled
dynamically right self-organizing
fashion between them raawk exactly but
not a blank slate in the head not an
MPhil homeless on the world absolutely
and that's why we get things like
imaginal constructs that can then
intersect and create potential right for
transfected participatory symbols like
the symbol of justice that then creates
a particular kind of frame that
integrates a lot and allows us to
participate with that
exactly that's well said so the the
imagine that we're using korbin sturm
which which I got where did I get I got
to talk to Tom Thomas Cheetham we have
we recorded a video together about
Corbin yeah so the note that's exactly
right
the imaginal it differs from the
imaginary imaginary in the imaginal is
not just a horizontal relationship to
some fictional object the imaginal if
you allow me this metaphor is also
vertical it's designed to access and
activate right these deeper levels of
knowing bringing us interact respectable
and ultimately participatory knowing of
something and yeah so because ultimately
but this goes I think to the court of
the point Greg ultimately we want a
participatory and perspectival knowing
of justice not not just just
propositional floor even procedural and
the more procedural we need all of it
yeah it all look good exactly here's
another thing that actually will connect
about what we need okay so in
psychotherapy there's an unbelievable
debate about you know empirically
supported treatments for example okay
well what you just said I think connects
actually immediately to a fundamental
debate okay in the field which is when
we started the field starts to try to do
empirically supported treatments it's
actually trying to create a set of
propositions and procedures okay that
are then enacted upon some system and
when it's a recipe its propositional and
procedural which is very impersonal and
not IDEO graphic in the dynamic
participatory relation between two
unique individuals which is why the
humanists went crazy in relationship to
trying to impose a code on an
inductively generalizable code that's
true for all people at least
probabilistically that then gets imposed
but then it all immediately becomes an
impersonal procedural code that
intuitive desire for authentic unique
relating reacts against so there's a
real it's an interesting dynamic so we
this is thank you great that's a great
connection so so two things come up
so one is you know I'm engaged in this
project of trying to figure out what do
logos look like and whatnot electic it
and your that's totally relevant to what
you just talked about and then the other
thing is you know that therapy has a
transformative component to it not just
a representational component and that's
why you need the perspective another
participatory so that's coming in and
then I i I've read I wanted to ask you
so let's talk about those two points but
first a brief sort of empirical point
I've read some research show it I mean
two things that independent of whatever
techniques you're using or approach
rapport is the thing that's the single
most important predictor of how well
therapy goes and then I've also read
some meta reviews that saying a lot of
the evidence-based things like CBT are
now losing their effectiveness across
time because the older practitioners
advocated CBT but they had all this
implicit respectable and participatory
stuff and what's happened is all that's
been transmitted what there's kind of a
copying error what it's being reduced to
the recipe and so these these therapies
are actually losing their effectiveness
as we as we move through time and so I
thought first of all are you like you
nodding your head so it sounds like
that's familiar information to you right
so rapport isn't exactly the word I
would use its alliance okay there's a
technical thing around Alliance and what
and the essence of Alliance and really I
run and of course a lot of this is very
complicated at the level of language
yeah it would meaning our our language
games and then what is actually just
circular and and all of that but what is
absolutely the case as far as I'm
concerned is that the psychosocial
relational process variables okay
documented over and over empirically so
empirically the humanists were basically
right in the sense that to the extent
that you establish a relationship
that has good flow okay a shared
understanding of your trouble and your
healing and we have a shared
understanding of the tasks you get those
ingredients together and that's
associated with good outcome right okay
okay okay that's what I was referring to
general common factors and it doesn't
really matter if your language game is
CBT or if it's a bona fide psychodynamic
or if it's emotion focused or or if it's
an existential I mean if you do that and
then we track people and it has these
ingredients and then you get basically
in the opening chapter of my book in my
original book is called from racing
horses to seeing the elephant right and
it comes from my history in
psychotherapy when I came from a CBT
tradition thinking that that was like oh
the science so CBT is good and then I
realized actually that's basically BS
when you get inside of it the fact of
the matter is this is ten times more
complicated than that
and none of the paradigms traditional
bonafide paradigms win but actually
that's these processes okay and what I'm
convinced in fact you were your
knowledge system just gave me the
language as to why I was convinced I was
always convinced that we didn't get the
scientific humanistic dialectics and
dynamic right you know we didn't have
the right language in fact that program
I directed on the part of still but that
I director for 12 years was explicitly
scientific humanistic in his orientation
and that is we would draw on scientific
language concepts and principles we
wouldn't be talking about God and
praying to God as psychologists but we
would be talking about a language of
science terms and then impute that and
look at the research evidence and then
put it in a unique IDEO graphic
participatory relation right right
excellent right and and that and that is
and that making sure you have the space
okay
you know like because I would always
take okay so you're gonna read the
literature and say CBT is good for you
and then I walk into your office because
I have problems I spent four years with
Beck right and you're gonna what are you
gonna do start walking me through
automatic thoughts and you know I really
I'm gonna look at you and be like you're
a joke okay so
so the generalizability is you have to
put it in the unique particular and you
have to have the skills to participate
to do that and and that and that's a
unique and dynamic video graphic it's
got all of these elements okay can we
zoom in on this right now because I
think that's absolutely because that's
the pit that's the point because now
this is where it overlaps with the
broader concern I have about you know
getting the logos back breaking
monologic presentation of information
and bringing back the logos which
introduces aporia and challenges just to
aspiration and transformation because
you're obviously referencing those
processes within therapy but I know you
might have seen some of the dialogues
I'm having with people like guy sends
talked and I encircling practice where
people are trying to like take this up
to take this back up and and bring it
back into no no we got to adjust the
meaning crisis in addition to our
individual idiosyncratic
psychotherapeutic concerns we have
shared cultural existential concerns
that need to be addressed so if you'll
allow me and and and then you know I'm
glad I'm talking to you because this is
going to pose you with sort of a
significant challenge but you know I
trust you so that that's what basically
I'm safe like what I want to do is try
to get you know and what I mean is you
know I hope you're trusting me I'm not
here to dice I think we're playing
together good part of part of it is part
of part of Villalobos though is to do
exactly what you talked about make sure
that we have an alliance make sure that
right that we're here together and
that's right you have a cooperative
coding of what we're doing and stuffing
like right so I want to zoom in on
because you I think you put your finger
on something that I want to unpack more
and you have it you kinda have a
terrific Bank of expertise and
experience you alluded to the these sets
of skills and I think you you're also
alluding to like sensibilities and
sensitivities right that you're bringing
in that are something beyond sets of
propositions or even individual
techniques that's fair that's a fair
representation under percent like what
are they sorry I warned you would be a
challenging question but I know you put
a lot of thought into this because you
teaching others and you have proud of
them for a long time you are a
leadership position what what is this I
mean the first competence of you that we
have is self-awareness and interpersonal
Grace competency ok so so who are you ok
what do you bring you know what how do
you say it propositional II and do you
understand it
procedurally participatory what I am
right okay so so I need to know that and
then I need to know how to match myself
other you know pairing so that I'm gonna
know what I am and know how to read who
I'm with ok and know how to adjust in a
dynamic interactive flow capacity the
dance between me and that ok if it's ok
with you do you mind if I interrupt at
sort of I mean so that for right again
that's really that's really crucial
because you see this I mean this is the
this this is the the major I mean Sarah
hablo rapid arguing for this and
Gonzalez on their books on Socratic
dialogo subscribe practice right the
idea and and more is doing it to in
Socratic self-knowledge that this
ability to enter into via logos is
deeply dependent upon and afforded by a
specific and profound kind of
self-knowledge because that's what you
were just talking about there and you
said it you you said it's not just your
beliefs or your image there's there's
more to that because you then said it
allows you to it goes back to this
mutual shaping I was talking about
earlier it allows you to engage in the
mutual shaping with your with your
client I take it so I'm sorry I I hope
you're not frustrate I want to slow down
and what's this self not what's that
self knowing right right is this okay
with you what I'm doing the course yeah
yeah yeah absolutely so I mean you know
in our world certainly a lot of that is
that well why do we really encourage
people to go to therapy right why why in
our supervision do we you know as
supervisors notice when people get
anxious notice when people you know
avoid certain topics notice people have
certain kinds of tics and why do we make
that in a in a tactful way but in also
in a direct way why do we make that
conscious mmm I know because you got a
deal with your shadow the thing you did
with Anderson Todd you know that I was a
wonderful in there if I get that name
perfect so he is narrative at the end of
that where he hates that guy you know
that talkative know-it-all guy which by
the way this is a particular narrative
that I could relate to okay and then you
split it off okay because I yes I talk a
lot no I'm not an arrogant know-it-all
got right but that guy is I know I don't
right so that was a wonderful moment in
which our tendency to justify
consciously splits us off from some
aspects of ourselves so that's a
conscious relative to who we are there's
also all the stuff that we talk about
well I'm a white guy you know you know
in a middle age that comes from a
particular background well it's the
salience factor of that if all of a
sudden I sit down with somebody from
India you know or whatever of course so
so it's that kind of those are
propositional elements and then there's
just a lot of immersion right you know
like you were talking about like Tai Chi
I think you know it's just sort of like
you know you got to get in there and do
it and get some feedback and create that
immediate you know feedback flow so so
there's that and let me also say there's
in the unified framework okay the
unified framework argues that we have a
relation of pre propositional relational
system of adaptation well that I map
through what's called the influence
matrix okay and that influence matrix is
the way we create intuitive self other
representational spaces right and place
ourselves on vertical axes of power you
know briefly horizontal reactions of
affiliation autonomy axes of engagement
and we're constantly fine-tuning those
kinds of things and we're constantly
then having an intuitive sense of
ourself in relation okay so when you
were saying is this okay is this okay
right
you were intuitively checking oh gosh am
i dominating am i pushing this I want to
make sure we're gonna do right
exactly thank you that's that was good I
one of the things I think that's
important I've been talking to guy about
this is the degree to which in genuine
dia logos you can move between
explication and then pointing to how the
dialogue itself is exemplifying a lot of
the stuff you want to be talking about
so you're constantly moving back between
sort of theory in theory a-- so i so let
me let me sort of this is what i heard
you saying i heard you saying no we're
not talking about sort of people's you
know just their sort of standard sort of
autobiography or you know the beliefs
they have about you know you're not
discarding that but that's massively
insufficient what you're trying to get
at is you're trying to get out how to
process the the ongoing continual
dynamic process of how they're assuming
an identity and assigning identities to
things is actually skewing their their
perspective it's it's the lens through
which and it's a two-way lens it's a
lens through which they're seeing the
world and themselves and you're trying
to get them if you'll allow me to sort
of do this right no no yes and become
aware of that become aware of how the
identification the co identification
process and the salience Landscaping are
deeply interpenetrating and bound
together and that's a that's a profound
kind of well that's that I could see
that or I could see why first of all two
things I can see why that really
requires you know you you be in therapy
or you know practice you know you have
undergone therapy is that the right word
in order to practice therapy sure that
brings me to the the point that because
this sounds like a very and this is
again deeply Socratic this is a deeply
threatening thing to do I would imagine
this kind of self knowing that you're
talking about yes yes because it's and
again I'll put it in the language of the
unified theory as to why it's the idea
essentially that shapes the human eye
this who I as an I am is a is a mental
organ of justification in other words
it's fundamentally sits to give an
account of the self in this social field
that legitimizes some aspect of it right
by definition that also creates a shadow
of what is not legitimate generally
right
and so what's threatening is that the
system will have consistency it will
have it certain biases
confirmation biases and tendencies and
that will create a cognitive stability
that if you challenge will get cognitive
dissonance right and then you get
anxiety and psychodynamic defense that
tries to re-stabilize and split off and
so it's very hard to have the courage to
enter into that space and to open
oneself up and say oh my god maybe I am
kind of an arrogant person or maybe I am
really insecure about this and I
compensate through that and now all of a
sudden as I encounter that it's like uh
but if you're held as you encounter it
you can then include and transcend it
rather than split it off this is
beautiful great case so what we've done
is we've shown right now that we've said
you know the the do logos depends on the
self knowing but notice in the end how
the self knowing in turn depends on the
do logos if I'm not in the dialogue the
therapeutic dialogue I can't actually
get the self knowing that I need to
enter in properly into dialogue is that
a fair and it goes to our relational
system and the fundamental structure of
ourselves as social animals James mark
Baldwin one of the greatest
developmental psychological
developmental theorists says ego and
alter are born together yes right so
it's sort of like and that's what the
the influence matrix says it's not
yourself it's self in relation to other
that we carry in our internal working
models you know our history of
appearance I mean this is classic
psychodynamic insight is I think you
were in a conversation was it with
Anderson ties it's like we are we know
our parents before we know ourselves so
look at the relational aspect in the
mirroring of course Mayer neurons and
all that stuff but you know absolutely
steeply relation okay so I found this
first move I think this I found this
tremendously elucidating you know that
like I said how we really dug deeply
into the mutual affordance of self
knowing and deilogos so that was you
said that's the first thing but I hope I
think that the interruption was was
fruitful right all right so that was the
first thing you look for incompetence
now take me if you can date like lates
maybe we could do this step by step then
what's your layer beyond that
and then we can try to unpack that well
the the it actually this is still
competence level one is really itself
and then interpersonal grace basically
the and it is sort of this artistic
impression of somebody's capacity to
enter in to various kinds of relations
with a high degree of probabilistic
outcome that they will achieve flow and
dance at a very basic level for instance
your capacity to be say empathetic and
compassionate with another okay but
there would also be cognitive components
right there you know to reframe yeah
yeah take a level I mean if you go back
to the oldest stuff and assertiveness
training right you you when do you err
on the side of passiveness when you err
on the side of aggressiveness how do you
speak with I statements instead of your
this and and those kinds of things so
you can create propositional skill you
know knowledge okay but then of course
as you know as our as we were discussing
it's there's one thing to know
conceptually how to shoot a basketball
there's another shoot a basketball right
there's a know one thing to know you
know and and people you know there's a
there's a whole set of ideas for example
on people that are on the spectrum you
know the spectrum right and if you know
simon baron-cohen z-- work on this the
idea is mind blindness is a particular
kind of issue and so without getting too
much into it but people who write neuro
a typical in relation will often have
difficulty on picking up on fine-grain
subtleties that other people that have
particular kinds of capacities I'm sure
you've met people that are unbelievably
good at just instantaneously tracking
you know and making you feel known you
know and and and just enter into that
with you before you know with very
little knowledge of you in the
background they should know Anderson
Anderson thought is particularly gifted
very much so I I sort of divine that you
probably are as well
so once so you you get you get this and
then you do you the grace is kind of an
you're looking for again you said
probabilistically it's not deterministic
we brought in general can people can
they sort of play with the parameters of
dialogue so that emerges is that is that
is that way right and we and then we
particularly look you know as
psychotherapists we're particularly
looking for those emotionally hot so see
emotionally hot episodes okay and then
your capacity to stay engaged and
skillful in those things so that would
be when you get activated you know
somebody says something that clashes
with your belief value said somebody
says you know how do you approach them
how do you in fact the whole we stopped
briefly about calm mo that's integrative
psycho technology that psychological
mind calm mo is exactly the set of sort
of encapsulated psycho technologies are
oriented towards fostering that let's
take a moment for you to I think that's
important that that connection you just
make I'm familiar with it because you've
been in discussion with me but I can see
that you know I can first see that you
know some of my listeners might that
acronym might have gone by too fast
no no but you breathe it so I think
there's two points there's two points
you look so the next sort of level of
competence you're looking for is their
ability to enter into what did you call
them socio emotional hot sponses is that
great catch and then they have to
maintain and notify want to sort of get
people to pay attention to this a
presence of mine and that's a
normativity of perspective a milling
remaining it's getting that sense of
presence which is different from
propositional conviction or even your
skills are working well can you say
present why can you be presence of mind
and you have a particular psycho
technology beyond my term for a 40-watt
i now call it that so unpack call them
over us but again right so actually
we'll do it real fast I now introduce
this this is another thing I get from
you I spend a lot of time with you John
you don't know it
okay so now the first thing I'll do is
calm body right okay so find your
centerline saber your body you know five
minutes a day I do that right thanks for
you okay so and now that I just opens me
up actually to a whole bunch of
meditative kinds of things so calm body
okay and then what I was developing was
psychological mindfulness okay what do I
mean by that
it's a presence of your capacity when we
come into psychotherapy what we're
actually engaged in is a psychological
mindfulness basically what we're trying
to do is increase awareness in a
non-judgmental accepting way of the
person the situation they're in their
problem possibilities it's basically so
then if we have a sense as where what
does that look like that environment
well then can you create that
prospectively in your head can you open
up a space where you see yourself in
this way step outside of your
subjectivity and become the object of
your attention and that's a mo that's
your metacognitive observer
so that's calm mo of calm what now are
in calm mind and what we're trying to do
is cultivate a better cognitive observer
that can step outside the flow where the
flow becomes the object of our attention
right okay so it's a meta move outside
of the stream so and so the stream
becomes an observer Segel has the idea
that mindfulness is in fact an ability
to internalize mindsight resonance yes
well that would be very very good system
with that okay and then the question is
well how do you achieve resonance what
is the and this gets into then and I
like Siegel by the way is a very very
interesting an interpersonal
neurobiology is a great integrative
frame of reference okay that cuts across
a wide variety so now son yes but now we
want to create resonance well what is
what what are the attitudinal signals
and and frames that we want to offer to
do that okay and calm is an acronym that
gives you the attitudinal frames of
reference and it starts with the word
curiosity right
so Curie so we want an open and
wandering mind that ask questions and
explores okay rather than one that
closes down and a certain lose and
closure you know they're Zeke's closure
right there's all this emerging work on
people who prematurely seek cognitive
closure that's right they want an
answers they know what to do right they
do they need to make sense out of it
quickly is a state of anxiety and then
you know and we and so then there's
there's that and each one of these you
can put them on a continuum so you can
you know curiosity can go to its
opposite okay then the next one is
acceptance okay so call the a and kamas
acceptance and this this ranges anywhere
from Buddhist notions to add attachment
to dialectical behavior therapy of
distress tolerance the capacity to hold
one's experience and say it is what it
is the capacity to be and ideally be
okay in a Buddha mind okay so that's the
second the L is loving compassion okay
this is holding people with dignity and
respect
wishing they didn't suffer and that's
very much is true for me as soon as to
you in creating a meta M et ta the frame
of mind an Eastern way and then finally
M am stance am motivated toward valued
states of being in the short and long
term mmm so in the short term is like
okay I'm in the proximal situation what
do I want out of this hour okay and if I
get into a fight with somebody how do I
want it to end as I walk out the door
that's short term and then ultimately
the long term okay the who do across all
the way up to what some people in what's
called act is a particular kind of
therapy they also use the exercise of
eulogy values okay so what what do you
want somebody to say at your funeral
that would connect to some sort of
divine double image we're deeply
aspirational yes exactly when I create
an image of what it is we could be and
then utilize that for relevance
realization down line in the imaginal
sense of image in the imaginal sense not
imaginary
right
exactly and so that we can see and know
and make and create it through this
particular kind of working symbol right
and then it becomes co-creative you know
that's the beauty oh so so do you do a
lot of like I mean I've as you know I
teach people the past now I teach them
that I teach them Tai Chi Chuan I take
them to courses when you're like so do
you spend a lot of time when you're
trying to move people into this deeper
level of confidence are you doing lots
of just exercise practice with comment
comment oh exercises is that if you do a
lot of that kind of thing yeah I mean
it's you you sort of hand people this
outline okay and certainly in the kinds
of psychotherapy and depending on where
they are they then bring it back each
week and and we sort of go through his
own a proximal development right what I
have not done what is it what is in the
works right now I mean this is now just
a psycho technology that I'm sharing and
inside the program that I operate you
know everyone knows what calm mo is and
it's useful okay it has not been turned
into a product you know that's like okay
and I don't mean that negatively I think
it really I see this as something that's
could be really useful I do hate I've
always had an issue with sort of like
you know try to create recipes but this
really is the kind of this is the kind
of psycho technology that I find does is
justice to both enough of the principles
and it's complete enough and yet it's
dynamic enough and fosters the
participatory
elements that does it and it doesn't get
corrupted by that's what I'm trying to
do is how do you create these things
that don't then just become algorithms
like CBT right that then get corrupted
and then turn people into little
cultural code robots if they're
successful which of course is really
what we don't want to do you know we
don't really want all right what's the
key to happiness oh well these are the
fourth step so now you're done so that's
really cool
know what I mean I mean the idea as a
whole school but what you just said
there at that last moment though the way
you're trying to frame it
like so almost like you always you want
to always be sort of zone of proximal
development you want to give enough so
that people right get a sense of what
you're doing but you don't want it you
don't want it as you say you don't want
to make it an algorithm they always have
to sort of tap into right the
transformative percent potential of
perspectival and participatory knowing
in order to keep getting what the
comment Oh calm actually means that's
what I was hearing from absolutely
absolutely
I'm really I'm also uh one of the things
that I've adopted lately very much is
the language of the soul spirit okay I
didn't used to use that but it is the I
you I used it soul in terms of its
original form actually I listen to you I
think you said it was sales that said
psyche is is the oldest is like mind
movement did I catch that correctly or
the idea yeah it's the idea I mean the
original is with his breath and wind but
it's moving a spectacle breath and wind
that seems to be what my mental state
share with with you know I'm obsessed
with this concept of psychology and you
know my basic definition of psychology
is a science of mental behavior okay so
mind movement and mental behavior I was
all excited anyway but but yes this is
this challenge okay to create this to
give people frames but then to create
their own development that's why I was
getting back to the soul thing is I love
the idea of the soul as you're a unique
particular perspectival you know place
in the world okay so so there is I say
there is no science of Greg Henriques
right you know because I'm the unique
IDEO graphic particular I'm not the
inductive generalized there's a science
of human behavior not really a science
of Greg and Rica's right but there could
be a soul of Gregory cos right right
right right
right I get that so now with that you
can then embrace the EU de Geographic
real right individual as that that's the
humanistic that's that that's the
fundamental challenge of humanism in
this regard so anyway that's use that so
it is that dialectic always
between sort of inductive general how
does it work but also how is it
contextualized in the unique particular
no no I think that's really valuable I
mean that that is so consonant with with
a beret Facebook you know Socratic
wisdom and platonic knowledge because
it's a product wisdom what you're
supposed to it's a book that's informing
the work I'm doing for after Socrates
but the the Socratic wisdom is exactly
that coming into a deep kind of
remembrance or use your language I'm
uncomfortable with it a bit for reasons
that you probably aware of but I'll use
your language nevertheless because I
want to play fair with you but I mean
the Socratic wisdom is to come into a
deep remembrance not just belief set but
like very much we're talking we're
coming into a deep remembrance of your
soul and that as you said is always in a
dialectic with the Platonic project of
trying to get generalized knowledge and
understand Plato crates the first
psychological theory that we're aware of
here are the three parts of the psyche
and all that which we keep rediscovering
in the West the three parts I read I
thought what you just said there was
deeply converging with her argument
because she was also saying you know
those two if you lose either one of
these polls you you're kind of moving
toward you're losing right you're you're
losing the Socratic project matrix
argument for sorta which is a very neo
platonic argument that you need to see
these two together you need to see the
the remembering like in sati remembering
of the soul but that always has to be in
dialogue and vice versa with as you said
the inductive generalization the the
knowledge the knowledge of you know what
human beings are and so I mean I try to
capture that in there in the dialog in
my own work between cognitive science of
existential phenomenological that's yeah
that's the humanistic and the scientific
I mean the we wrote about this in the
eleventh you know important to I use
your thing to look at myself and my tree
of knowledge inside you know the flat
light bulb flash that you know all
sudden it drew it out and I still to
this day I'm like God acts like the
whole thing
and it was this unbelievable
intersection between my unique
particular knowledge and my sati ila
it's like I remember this stuff you know
it was like it was there all along it
was this very very very powerful
experience along those lines so really
really cool well yeah yeah thank you for
sharing about that I thought I thought
in addition to its theoretical import I
thought it was a nice rhetorical
flourish I mean that as a compliment
because when you brought in that
personal story I think that gives people
a much more concrete and accessible
understanding of the kind of stuff they
were talking about right well I and I
think that's an and go to nod to your
point about participatory you know I
mean you know why that's how we embody
stuff right I mean why the
advertisements for getting money to say
Africa you know when they list three
million children you know propositional
e you get one thing when you see one
child right and then all the money flows
in and and the reason is because there's
a there's a participatory perspectival
connection to that that's very different
you know and so it's that juxtaposition
so I think there's a deep connection
than between these two things so you
remember I was talking about earlier how
there's this movement in genuine
dialogue between sort of explication of
an idea and then turning back
recursively and saying how is it
exemplified in what we're doing right
here now it's not moving between theory
and theory you're constantly doing that
and that seems to be a way in which
we're tapping into this point that
you've just made
we're constantly also trying to keep the
dialogue going between the soul and the
best knowledge we have of human nature
of illa-llah that's what I mean when I
talk about scientific humanistic
dialectic that's very very much alone
and I see good and see what what I'm
trying to do with the work I'm doing
with guy cents talk and with Christopher
master Pietro and Jordan Hall because
I'm trying to take that I'm trying to
take things like circling and some of
the work I've you know I had a couple
I've had a really a couple of really
interesting discussions with Edwin as
well with his embassy circling but I'm
trying to understand okay right how can
we take like say for example circling
and that this is a and guy is really
really involved in this so I want to I
want to pro please share credit here you
know commandest amount of work I'm doing
with Chris I hear what you're saying and
you want to give credit to guy and also
to Chris the chapter on dia logos and
all of that so but what I'm trying to
get at is take something like circling
which is about setting up this alliance
and getting the flow going right in
collective intelligence but then
introducing some of these more Socratic
elements into it that we've been talking
about here so that it's the circle is
not always just about circling and where
people are in their lives but you could
get the circle to circle around
circumambulate topics like yeah and
meeting making that we're not only
talking about but exemplifying in the
dialogue and we could move between
explication and exemplification we could
move between how we internalize it in
our soul and how we try to fit it into
our best science of human beings that's
what I want guy sometimes calls this
circling 2.0 that's what so that's well
that's unbelievably because then what
you're basically doing for my management
office see if I can put it in your
language you know is it's the
intersection of the four p's embodied
yes yes very much very very much totally
embodied enacted and enacted in a way
right that's open to what we were
talking about before that it there's an
emergence ability to it it can it can
transcend itself as a process it's not
my founded it can't be turned into a
recipe and an algorithm because it's
there's an ongoing constitutive
recognition that its ability to
transcend itself an emergence is what
this is ultimately all about that's
right that's right and we can follow a
line all the way up to relevance
realization and that I mean to me
I'm working with a southern a good
friend of mine Michaelmas Colo a
sophisticated developmental psychologist
and he you know talks about creating the
good society and how we need to build
bridges okay and what it fundamentally
it is is no he likes the kind of it's
the fear for self in other words I got
to protect myself and the love for the
other and how do we hold that in
particular ways and then how do we do it
so that we understand where the divide
is and then how do we bridge the divide
to create common ground okay that
grounds us you know and what I would say
from the tree of knowledge perspective
is we want to ground ourselves
propositional e in good justification
systems and we want to ground ourselves
relationally in in manifesting what I
call relational value that's being known
and valued by important others right
right we create that relational feel the
just of get or II feel as we engage in
these kinds of endeavors then we
actually are creating the common ground
through and through through the four P
level you know and that's the kind of
system that was a very nice piece of
integration you just did thank you for
that that was very good I like that
um so once once you get people sort of
you know getting a kind of expertise if
they even that's the right word with
calm mo what's next I mean where I I
keep turning back to the pedagogical
program that you're taking people
through cuz I really trying and we've
this is this is turn I so what I was
hoping for has come to fruition this has
turned out to be such a rich place to
zoom in and try and you know unpack it
very carefully so is that a culminating
thing or what what happens next
yeah I mean you know I'm very much
involved well I'm involved in lots of
different and so I got a lot of you know
but so actually you're right the unified
framework has three different sort of
really pieces okay one is a theory of
knowledge and wisdom writ large okay so
it's a medicine thetic med of psychology
new way of thinking about cyfle Asif II
really
to launch an Enlightenment 2.0 kind of
vision
I was I was telling my wife last night
because I had heard the mind and motion
kind of thing I was like yes we need to
take Newton's matter in motion and we
need to add a Concilium mind in motion
so there's that and then there's the
unit is this really unified theory of
psychology which then hones in on
cognitive science and all of that stuff
and then there's the unified approach
which is at the doctoral level ok how
would a doctoral level psychologist be
an applied professional ok and not learn
how to be in relation to the socio
emotional problems that people have and
then how to extract all of those things
out into psycho technologies that then
can be shared ok so you don't to be a
doctor alone psychology ok and and so
what calm mo out is is a really a
distillation of the applied principles
that can organize so see emotional
process especially when people get
bumped by you know defense and
activation and trouble and shadow and
conflict and then activate calm mo and
ok well I'm gonna have to start bringing
this towards closure but I would like I
want to invite you to have another one
of these discussions with me why yeah
it's a lot of fun and I found this
tremendously fruitful so I mean you've
given me you've written me some topics
and we can pick those up but there's a
general theme that we sort of background
it behind this that maybe we could fall
ground the next time we talk which is
and it you know and you alluded to it
explicitly a few times which is you know
this idea about what's the relationship
between science and spirituality for us
here now what does that mean not just
theoretically but the way we've been
talking in a way that gets a
transformative purchase on our lives so
that people can engage in the
transformations the cultivation of
wisdom etc that is needed to address
what I call the meaning crisis I'd like
to pick that up with you brilliant I
know and I'll throw out there the idea
that you know as you know we share
a series of emails and came to the
theory and practice of relevance
realized of transcendent realization yes
exactly and and I will tell you that
that day I had an hour-long conversation
of my father a former evangelical turned
atheist okay so he's on both sides of
the theist and then an atheist kind of
divided and I've been trying to
cultivate in a minute a non theist or
Cynthia's kind of view and I walked him
through the idea that you can transcend
your ego state you know and and create a
transcendent egoic right of perspective
and and if large numbers of people do
that ARCA potential to realize a world
and make and create a world that is
quite different and quite more
fulfilling and wiser and he really
really tapped that so we can really
let's do that I like that and I like
that I want to pick up on the connection
you also made to that idea about
transcendence realization and the the
discussion around theism atheism non-fee
non-theism and Cynthia 'sm which is
Alexander bar I've embraced it there's
some aspects and shades of bards work
you know that you know I have a slightly
different feel on but the concept of
Cynthia ism in my I have often said hey
I'm an American Cynthia found myself
saying that because I believe in the
idea of God or the God beyond God where
the create the divine double and embrace
the idea of that is a spiritual lodestar
I mean I used to be the scientific
atheist completely and now I really see
the modernist mentality cuts undercuts
the humanistic capacity for
transcendence in a deeply problematic
way and it doesn't have to and we can
all be better off if we if we see the
path for that Wow Greg that's such a
pregnant and provocative ending wait not
now everybody will definitely want to
tune in to our next conversation I
really look forward to it man so me too
I'm gonna end a recording right now